<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://www.eclipse.org/projects/project-plan.xsl"?>
<plan plan-format="1.0" xmlns="http://www.eclipse.org/project/plan" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      name="Project Name">
   <release projectid="modeling.mdt" version="Indigo"/>
   <introduction>
     <html:div>
<html:p>
This document lays out the feature and API set for the
sixth annual release of the Eclipse Object Constraint Language (MDT OCL)
Project, version 3.1.0.

A late requirement to use Xtext rather than IMP to support editing meant that many 3.0.0 facilities
were not fully developed in time for release 3.0.0. Resolution of evaluator issues and library usability
were held back, and the editors provided only as examples. Interim milestones, or if necessary an interim
3.1.0 release, are intended to resolve quality issues in the editors.
The 3.1.0 release (for Indigo) should prepare for full integration
of the new editors and make the library model-driven. Switchover of the old APIs to the new functionality
and renaming of examples plugins should occur immediately after Indigo so that OCL clients have the
entire Indigo+1 development cycle to exploit the enhancements that will appear in 3.2.0.

New external APIs are planned to provide interchangeability with alternate OCL products.
The existing external APIs should be unaffected, will be deprecated after Indigo, but may be
retained indefinitely.

New semi-internal parsing APIs are planned to resolve a number of hard problems and to provide
compatibility between the LPG and Xtext parsers. The existing semi-internal parsing APIs will
be retained in so far as possible, but will be deprecated in Indigo. The project team anticipates
working with major consumers in the release after Indigo to assist in migration to the new APIs.
</html:p>
<html:p>
<html:i><html:b>Note</html:b> that, since the 
<html:a href="http://www.omg.org/spec/OCL/2.3/Beta2/PDF">OMG OCL 2.3</html:a>
standard suffers from significant ambiguities and conflicts making a compliant implementation impossible,
<html:b>Eclipse (MDT) OCL 3.1.0</html:b> release is best endeavours to establish a coherent interpretation
of the OMG OCL 2.3 and to prototype resolutions and auto-generation of the OMG OCL 2.4 standard. Two of the Eclipse (MDT) OCL
committers are also members of the OMG Revision Task Force that resolves the specification issues.</html:i>
</html:p>
<html:p>
</html:p>
<html:p>
</html:p>
     </html:div>
   </introduction>
   <release_deliverables>
     <html:div>
The release deliverables for the Eclipse (MDT) OCL 3.1 release have the same form as 
is found in most Eclipse projects, namely:
<html:ul>
<html:li>OCL SDK (includes runtime, sources, examples, and documentation) (downloadable and update site).</html:li>
<html:li>OCL runtime binary distribution (downloadable and update site).</html:li>
<html:li>OCL stand-alone binary distribution (downloadable).</html:li>
<html:li>OCL tests (downloadable)</html:li>
<html:li>OCL examples (downloadable and update site)</html:li>
</html:ul>
Eclipse (MDT) OCL 3.1.0  source code will be available as versions tagged "R3_1" in the project's CVS repository.
     </html:div>
   </release_deliverables>
   <release_milestones>
      <preamble>
         <html:div>
Release milestones occur at roughly 6 week intervals and follow the
Platform milestone releases by approximately 1 week; that is, until the
final 3.7 release of the Platform, upon which MDT OCL and other projects
will release simultaneously. As Eclipse OCL is a dependency of numerous
other projects, Eclipse OCL will deliver its milestones at the +1
schedule in accordance with the schedule below.
         </html:div>
      </preamble>
<milestone date="Monday 18 August 2010" milestone="3.1.0M1"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 27 September 2010" milestone="3.1.0M2"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 8 November 2010" milestone="3.1.0M3"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 13 December 2010" milestone="3.1.0M4"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 31 January 2011" milestone="3.1.0M5"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 14 March 2011" milestone="3.1.0M6"><html:div>API freeze</html:div></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 2 May 2011" milestone="3.1.0M7"><html:div>Feature Freeze</html:div></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 16 May 2011" milestone="3.1.0RC1"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 23 May 2011" milestone="3.1.0RC2"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 30 May 2011" milestone="3.1.0RC3"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 6 June 2011" milestone="3.1.0RC4"></milestone>
<milestone date="Monday 22 June 2011" milestone="Indigo"></milestone>
      <postamble><html:div>
      </html:div></postamble>
   </release_milestones>
   <target_environments>
     <html:div>
        In order to remain current, each Eclipse release targets reasonably
        current versions of the underlying operating environments. The Eclipse
        Object Constraint Language (OCL) project depends upon on the
        Platform and other projects, which are mostly "pure" Java. The 3.7
        release of the Eclipse Platform Project is written and compiled
        against version 5.0 of the Java Platform APIs, and targeted to run on
        version 5.0 of the Java Runtime Environment, Standard Edition. Eclipse OCL
        will target the same Java version as EMF and UML2, which currently require
        Java 5. Eclipse Platform SDK 3.7 will be tested and validated on a
        number of reference platforms. MDT OCL will be tested and validated
        against a subset of those listed for the platform.
     </html:div>
     <internationalization>
          <html:div>
The Eclipse Platform is designed as the basis
for internationalized products. The user interface elements provided
by the Eclipse SDK components, including dialogs and error messages,
are externalized. The English strings are provided as the default
resource bundles. As a result, the Eclipse OCL
project will provide English strings in its default bundles and be
localized to a subset of those locales offered by the Platform.
          </html:div>
     </internationalization>
   </target_environments>
   <compatibility_with_previous_releases>
       <html:div>
The Eclipse OCL 3.1 project
will be developed in parallel, and released simultaneously, with the
following projects. 
<html:ul>
    <html:li>Eclipse Platform SDK version 3.7</html:li>
    <html:li>Eclipse Modeling Framework (EMF) version 2.7</html:li>
    <html:li>Model Development Tools (MDT) UML2 version 3.2</html:li>
</html:ul>
<html:p>
As described above, the Eclipse OCL 3.1.0 release should address usability of the editors.
The main OCL plugins should be unaffected,
but the associated examples plugins may be revised significantly.

Again as described above, the Eclipse OCL 3.2.0 release for Juno will introduce significant new APIs
in a new namespace that replaces the old. The old namespace will be deprecated once all
Simultaneous Release projects have migrated to the new namespace.  
</html:p>
<html:p>
</html:p>
       </html:div>
   </compatibility_with_previous_releases>
   <themes_and_priorities>
     <preamble>
         <html:div>
A list of project requirements and agreed upon
implementation time frames is found in this document. For the
milestones listed in this document, a set of overall themes is used
to indicate what major set of functionalities is to be concentrated
on for each. These themes are presented below, while the requirements
document and associated Bugzilla entries are left to those wanting
more detailed information on each.
         </html:div>
     </preamble>
        <theme name="Compliance">
            <description>
                <html:div>
This theme addresses issues related to the OMG OCL 2.3 specification adoption. The bugs related to the inherited deviations
of the Eclipse OCL implementation from the OCL 2.0 specification (and consequently, OCL 2.3) also appear here.

It is anticipated that fixes for the majority of the target 3.2.0 will appear in the
revised Eclipse OCL Examples code in 3.1.0, but this will not be promoted to replace the
traditional behaviour until 3.2.0.
                </html:div>
            </description>
            <committed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Compliance&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=VERIFIED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED">
            </committed>
            <proposed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Compliance&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED">
            </proposed>
            <deferred
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Compliance&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo-">
            </deferred>
        </theme>
        <theme name="Release Currency">
            <description>
                <html:div>
The Eclipse OCL project will maintain currency with its
dependencies, in particular with the EMF and MDT UML2 projects.
                </html:div>
            </description>
            <committed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Release+Currency&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=VERIFIED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED">
            </committed>
            <proposed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Release+Currency&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED">
            </proposed>
            <deferred
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Release+Currency&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo-">
            </deferred>
        </theme>
        <theme name="Usability">
            <description>
                <html:div>
This theme addresses the need for extensibility and usability improvements
of the Eclipse OCL language implementation and APIs.

It is anticipated that fixes for the majority of the target 3.2.0 will appear in the
revised Eclipse OCL Examples code in 3.1.0, but this will not be promoted to replace the
traditional behaviour until 3.2.0.
                </html:div>
            </description>
            <committed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Usability&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=VERIFIED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED">
            </committed>
            <proposed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Usability&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED">
            </proposed>
            <deferred
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Usability&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo-">
            </deferred>
        </theme>
        <theme name="Specification">
            <description>
                <html:div>
This theme addresses issues related to prototyping resolutions of problems in the OMG OCL 2.3 specification and enhancements in future specifications. OMG issues
will be raised and RTF proposed resolutions submitted in order to  

It is anticipated that fixes for the majority of the target 3.2.0 will appear in the
revised Eclipse OCL Examples code in 3.1.0, but this will not be promoted to replace the
traditional behaviour until 3.2.0.
                </html:div>
            </description>
            <committed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Specification&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=VERIFIED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED">
            </committed>
            <proposed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Specification&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=3.1.0&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo%2B&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED">
            </proposed>
            <deferred
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;status_whiteboard_type=substring&amp;status_whiteboard=Specification&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;field0-0-0=flagtypes.name&amp;type0-0-0=equals&amp;value0-0-0=indigo-">
            </deferred>
        </theme>
   </themes_and_priorities>
   <appendix name="Legal Notices">
        <html:div>
<html:ul>
<html:li>Java is a trademark or a registered trademark of Oracle Corporation.</html:li>
<html:li>OCL and OMG are trademarks or registered trademarks of the Object Management Group, Inc.</html:li>
<html:li>All other products or company names are mentioned for identification purposes only, and
    may be trademarks or service marks of their respective owners.</html:li>
</html:ul>
        </html:div>
   </appendix>
</plan>