<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://www.eclipse.org/projects/project-plan.xsl"?>
<plan plan-format="1.0">
	<release projectid="modeling.mdt.ocl" version="1.3.0" />
	<introduction><![CDATA[
	    <p>
	    This document lays out the feature and API set for the
		fourth release of the Eclipse Object Constraint Language (MDT OCL)
		Project, version 1.3.0. This project plan inherits from the Modeling
		Project Plan, which should be referenced when consulting this
		individual project plan.
		</p><p>
		<i><b>Note</b> that, depending on the nature of the anticipated OCL® 2.1
		revised specification from the OMG™, <b>MDT OCL may require incompatible
		API changes</b> and release as version <b>2.0.0</b>.
		</p>
		]]>
    </introduction>
	<release_deliverables>
     <![CDATA[
    The release deliverables have the same form as is found in most Eclipse projects, namely:
<ul>
<li>MDT OCL source code release, available as versions tagged "R1_3" in the project's CVS repository.</li>
<li>MDT OCL SDK (includes runtime, sources, examples, and documentation) (downloadable and update site).</li>
<li>MDT OCL runtime binary distribution (downloadable and update site).</li>
<li>MDT OCL stand-alone binary distribution (downloadable).</li>
<li>MDT OCL tests (downloadable)</li>
</ul>
  ]]>
	</release_deliverables>
	<release_milestones>
		<preamble><![CDATA[
		Release milestone occurring at roughly 6 week intervals and follow the
		Platform milestone releases by approximately 1 week; that is, until the
		final 3.5 release of the Platform, upon which MDT OCL and other projects
		will release simultaneously. As MDT OCL is a dependency of numerous
		other projects, MDT OCL will deliver its milestones within one week of
		the Eclipse Platform. It is anticipated that MDT OCL will synchronize its
		milestones with the Galileo milestone schedule.
       ]]>
		</preamble>
		<milestone date="08/13/2008" milestone="M1"></milestone>
		<milestone date="09/24/2008" milestone="M2"></milestone>
		<milestone date="11/05/2008" milestone="M3"></milestone>
		<milestone date="12/17/2008" milestone="M4"></milestone>
		<milestone date="02/03/2009" milestone="M5"></milestone>
		<milestone date="03/16/2009" milestone="M6">API freeze
		</milestone>
		<milestone date="05/04/2009" milestone="M7">Feature Freeze</milestone>
		<milestone date="05/18/2009" milestone="RC1"></milestone>
		<milestone date="05/25/2009" milestone="RC2"></milestone>
		<milestone date="06/01/2009" milestone="RC3"></milestone>
		<milestone date="06/08/2009" milestone="RC4"></milestone>
		<milestone date="06/15/2009" milestone="RC5"></milestone>
		<milestone date="06/28/2009" milestone="1.3.0"></milestone>
		<postamble><![CDATA[
      MDT OCL will produce maintenance releases to align with the Ganymede SR
      releases, that includes the Eclipse Platform 3.4.1 and 3.4.2 releases.
      MDT OCL may produce interim maintenance releases in addition to these in
      order to satisfy clients requests.
<ul><li>Friday, August 15, 2008 - MDT OCL 1.2.1 maintenance release</li>
<li>Friday, September 26, 2008 - MDT OCL 1.2.2 maintenance release (Ganymede Service Release 1)</li>
<li>Friday, February 27, 2009 - MDT OCL 1.2.3 maintenance release (Ganymede Service Release 2)</li>
<li>A list of issues indicated for the 1.2.x maintenance stream can be found in
 bugzilla, or by using links on maintenance stream build pages.</li></ul> 
      ]]></postamble>
	</release_milestones>
	<target_environments>
		In order to remain current, each Eclipse release targets reasonably
		current versions of the underlying operating environments. The Eclipse
		Object Constraint Language (MDT OCL) project depends upon on the
		Platform and other projects, which are mostly "pure" Java. The 3.5
		release of the Eclipse Platform Project is written and compiled
		against version 1.4 of the Java Platform APIs, and targeted to run on
		version 1.4 of the Java Runtime Environment, Standard Edition. MDT OCL
		will target the same Java version as EMF and UML2, which currently require
		Java 5. Eclipse Platform SDK 3.5 will be tested and validated on a
		number of reference platforms. MDT OCL will be tested and validated
		against a subset of those listed for the platform.
		<internationalization> The Eclipse Platform is designed as the basis
			for internationalized products. The user interface elements provided
			by the Eclipse SDK components, including dialogs and error messages,
			are externalized. The English strings are provided as the default
			resource bundles. As a result, the MDT OCL
			project will provide English strings in its default bundles and be
			localized to a subset of those locales offered by the Platform. This
			plan will be updated to indicate which locales will be provided and
			the time frame for availability.</internationalization>
	</target_environments>
	<compatibility_with_previous_releases>
		Compatibility of Release 1.2: The MDT OCL project
		will be developed in parallel, and released simultaneously, with the
		following projects. As stated above, each milestone release of the
		MDT OCL project will be compatible with the
		corresponding milestones for each of these projects, and delivered the
		appropriate offset.
		<ul>
			<li>Eclipse Platform SDK version 3.5</li>
			<li>Eclipse Modeling Framework (EMF) version 2.5</li>
			<li>Model Development Tools (MDT) UML2 version 2.3</li>
		</ul>
		Therefore, the MDT OCL initial release will be
		compatible with these versions and will publish binary and source
		compatibilities with migration guides on subsequent releases.
	</compatibility_with_previous_releases>
	<themes_and_priorities>
		<preamble> A list of project requirements and agreed upon
			implementation time frames is found in this document. For the
			milestones listed in this document, a set of overall themes is used
			to indicate what major set of functionalities is to be concentrated
			on for each. These themes are presented below, while the requirements
			document and associated Bugzilla entries are left to those wanting
			more detailed information on each.</preamble>
		<theme name="Release Currency">
			<description>The MDT OCL project will maintain currency with its
			dependencies, in particular advances in the EMF and MDT UML2 projects.
			Additionally, as an implementation of the OMG's OCL 2.0 specification,
			the MDT OCL project will maintain currency with the revised 2.1
			specification.</description>
			<committed
				bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=substring&amp;short_desc=%5BRelease+Currency%5D&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=RC&amp;target_milestone=M1&amp;target_milestone=M2&amp;target_milestone=M3&amp;target_milestone=M4&amp;target_milestone=M5&amp;target_milestone=M6&amp;target_milestone=M7&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=plan&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED">
			</committed>
			<proposed
				bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=substring&amp;short_desc=%5BRelease+Currency%5D&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=1.3.0&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=plan&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED">
			</proposed>
			<deferred
				bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=substring&amp;short_desc=%5BRelease+Currency%5D&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=---&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=plan&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED">
			</deferred>
		</theme>
		<theme name="Extensibility">
			<description>The Object Constraint Language is re-used and extended
			by other language specifications, in particular the OMG MOF® Query/View/Transformation
			family of languages.  This theme addresses the need for extensibility
			of the MDT OCL language implementation and APIs.</description>
            <committed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=substring&amp;short_desc=%5BExtensibility%5D&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=RC&amp;target_milestone=M1&amp;target_milestone=M2&amp;target_milestone=M3&amp;target_milestone=M4&amp;target_milestone=M5&amp;target_milestone=M6&amp;target_milestone=M7&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=plan&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED">
            </committed>
            <proposed
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=substring&amp;short_desc=%5BExtensibility%5D&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=1.3.0&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=plan&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED">
            </proposed>
            <deferred
                bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=substring&amp;short_desc=%5BExtensibility%5D&amp;classification=Modeling&amp;product=MDT&amp;component=OCL&amp;target_milestone=---&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=plan&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED">
            </deferred>
		</theme>
	</themes_and_priorities>
   <appendix name="Legal Notices">
   <![CDATA[
   <ul>
   <li>Java is a trademark or a registered trademark of Sun Microsystems, Inc.</li>
   <li>OCL and OMG are trademarks or registered trademark of the Object Management Group™, Inc.</li>
   <li>All other products or company names are mentioned for identification purposes only, and
       may be trademarks or service marks of their respective owners.</li>
   </ul>
   ]]>
   </appendix>
</plan>